<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.33.0-wmf.19</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>José Holebas</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20562000</id>
    <revision>
      <id>886007695</id>
      <parentid>886007637</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-03-03T19:07:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2A02:587:3D01:2C00:C08A:835:13F6:511B</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36686">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox football biography
| name = José Holebas
| image = 20130814 AT-GR Jose Holebas 2371 (cropped).jpg
| image_size = 200
| caption = Holebas with [[Greece national football team|Greece]] in 2013
| fullname = José Lloyd Cholevas&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://tournament.fifadata.com/documents/FWC/2014/pdf/FWC_2014_SQUADLISTS.PDF |title=FIFA World Cup Brazil 2014: List of players|publisher=FIFA|date=14 June 2014 |accessdate=14 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| birth_date = {{birth date and age|1984|6|27|df=y}}&lt;ref name="Premier League"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.premierleague.com/en-gb/players/profile.overview.html/jose-holebas |title=Premier League Player Profile José Holebas |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=2016 |publisher=Barclays Premier League |access-date=7 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| birth_place = [[Aschaffenburg]], West Germany
| height = 1.84 m&lt;ref name="Premier League"/&gt;
| position = [[Left back]] / [[Left midfielder]]
| currentclub = [[Watford F.C.|Watford]]
| clubnumber = 25
| youthyears1 =
| youthclubs1 = FC Südring
| youthyears2 =
| youthclubs2 = FC Kleinwallstadt
| youthyears3 =
| youthclubs3 = TSV Teutonia Obernau
| youthyears4 = 2002–2005
| youthclubs4 = SV 1910 Aschaffenburg-Damm
| years1 = 2005–2006
| clubs1 = [[:de:FC Viktoria Kahl|Viktoria Kahl]]
| caps1  = 33
| goals1 = 15
| years2 = 2006–2008
| clubs2 = [[TSV 1860 Munich II|1860 Munich II]]
| caps2  = 43
| goals2 = 12
| years3 = 2007–2010
| clubs3 = [[TSV 1860 Munich|1860 Munich]]
| caps3  = 74
| goals3 = 7
| years4 = 2010–2014
| clubs4= [[Olympiacos F.C.|Olympiacos]]
| caps4  = 94
| goals4 = 9
| years5 = 2014–2015
| clubs5= [[A.S. Roma|Roma]]
| caps5  = 24
| goals5 = 1
| years6 = 2015–
| clubs6= [[Watford F.C.|Watford]]
| caps6  = 96
| goals6 = 6
| nationalyears1 = 2011–2016
| nationalteam1 = [[Greece national football team|Greece]]
| nationalcaps1 = 38
| nationalgoals1 = 1
| club-update = 22:13, 3 March 2019 (UTC).
| nationalteam-update = 
}}
'''José Lloyd Cholevas''' ({{lang-el|Χοσέ Λόιντ Χολέβας}}; born 27 June 1984), known as '''José Holebas''' {{IPA-el|xoˈse xoˈlevas|}}, is a Greek professional [[Association football|footballer]] who plays as a [[Defender (association football)#Full-back|left back]] or a [[Midfielder#Wide midfielder|left midfielder]] for [[Watford F.C.|Watford]]. He played for the [[Greece national football team|Greek national team]] from 2011 to 2016.

==Early life==
Holebas was born in [[Aschaffenburg]], [[Bavaria]], West Germany, to a [[Greeks|Greek]] father, Achilles, from [[Trikala]], and a [[Uruguay]]an mother, Lowis.

==Personal life==
At the age of 18, Holebas became father to daughter Tanisha.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.bild.de/sport/fussball/loewen-chance-3490728.bild.html | title = Holebas: Löwen sind die Chance meines Lebens! | trans-title = Holebas: "Lions are the chance of my life" | language = German | publisher = [[Bild]] | accessdate = 7 January 2015| date = 16 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, Holebas married Diana Jäger, a German woman who also hails from Aschaffenburg. Holebas speaks German and English fluently and although he does not speak much [[Greek language|Greek]], he understands it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.main-netz.de/nachrichten/region/aschaffenburg/aschaffenburg-stadt/berichte/art4011,1658747 | title = Erst der Titel in Griechenland, dann die Hochzeit in der Heimat | trans-title = First the championship in Greece, then the wedding at home | language = German | publisher = Main-Netz.de | accessdate = 7 January 2015| date = 24 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Club career==
===Early years===
Holebas' first club was local youth team Südring, which he joined in 1992 when he was eight. He played at non-professional youth football teams in German football which included playing for Südring, FC Kleinwallstadt and TSV Teutonia Obernau until 2001, when his girlfriend got pregnant and José, at age 18, decided to temporarily give up football. He had to work the double shift as a warehouse assistant in order to financially support his family. A year later, in 2002 and with the guidance of his Uruguayan uncle, Alfonso, whom Holebas described as his "second father" and "who gave me the kicks I needed to get my life back on track," helped him begin playing football again. He played for local youth side Aschaffenburg-Damm from 2002 to 2005.&lt;ref name="pineza.gr"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.pineza.gr/index.php?option=com_k2&amp;view=item&amp;id=2908:ena-afierwma-sthn-apisteuth-zwi-tou-xose-xolempas&amp;Itemid=210 | title = Ένα αφιέρωμα στην απίστευτη ζωή του Χοσέ Χολέμπας | publisher = pineza.gr| date = 20 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Viktoria Kahl===
In 2005, Holebas was signed by German 6th-tier [[Landesliga Bayern-Nordwest]] club [[:de:FC Viktoria Kahl|FC Viktoria Kahl]]. Under manager Antonio Abbruzzese, he played as a striker and scored 15 goals in 33 appearances and finished among Landesliga's top scorers. [[TSV 1860 Munich|1860 Munich]] scouts approached him and Holebas joined their club in the summer of 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.thetoc.gr/athlitika/article/xose-xolebas-to-agori-me-ta-tatouaz| title = Χοσέ Χολέβας: Το αγόρι με τα τατουάζ| publisher = thetoc.gr| accessdate = 30 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1860 Munich===
[[File:Jose Holebas 1860 2009.JPG|thumb|left|150 px|Holebas training with 1860 Munich in 2009]]
In his first season in [[Munich]], Holebas was in 1860's [[TSV 1860 Munich II|second team]], where, at 22 years of age, he was considered "too old" by the club's youth academy coach, Ernst Tanner. Holebas officially made his debut for 1860 Munich II on 5 August 2006 in a [[Regionalliga Süd (1994–2012)|Regionalliga Süd]] game against [[TSG 1899 Hoffenheim|1899 Hoffenheim]]. A year later, in the summer of 2007, Holebas signed his first professional contract with the [[TSV 1860 Munich|first team]]. He  made his professional debut for the "Munich Lions" on 21 September 2007 at 23 years of age against [[FC St. Pauli|St. Pauli]], in a [[2. Bundesliga]] game.

Holebas accumulated three years of professional football experience in the German second tier with 1860 Munich, with the side finishing 11th in 2007–08, 12th in 2008–09 (while also dropping back to 1860 Munich II for a number of games) and 8th in 2009–10. In the summer of 2009,  new coach [[Ewald Lienen]], advised  25-year-old Holebas to stay back and play as a defending left-winger.

Holebas finished his five-season stint in Germany with both Viktoria Kahl and 1860 Munich, scoring a total of 34 goals in 154 games in all competitions. Despite initially disliking the club as a child due to being a childhood fan of 1860's fierce cross-city [[Munich derby|Munich rivals]] [[FC Bayern Munich|Bayern]], Holebas stated his changed opinion of the club that gave him his breakthrough in professional football, stating, "I'll forever be grateful to 1860 Munich."&lt;ref name="pineza.gr"/&gt;

===Olympiacos===
====2010–11 season====
Ewald Lienen left 1860 Munich to become the coach of [[Superleague Greece]] club [[Olympiacos F.C.|Olympiacos]]. Lienen signed Holebas for a transfer fee of €500,000. Holebas stated in an interview, "My father is Greek, but this is only the second time that I have come back to the country. When I was [here] first here, I was very young and do not remember many things, but I must say that I am very happy to play in the old country."

On 15 July 2010, Holebas made his debut for Olympiacos in a 5–0 away victory over [[Albania]]n club [[Besa Kavajë]] in the first leg of a [[2010–11 UEFA Europa League|Europa League second qualifying round]] tie. On 5 August, Olympiacos were knocked out of the [[UEFA Europa League]] by Israeli club [[Maccabi Tel Aviv F.C.|Maccabi Tel Aviv]], on the [[away goals rule]] and after a 2–2 draw. Olympiacos sacked Lienen; the new coach, [[Ernesto Valverde]], began to use Holebas both as a defending and an attacking left winger, depending on Olympiacos' opponent. Holebas scored his first goal for the club on 20 March 2011 in a 6–0 home league win over [[AEK Athens F.C.|AEK Athens]], which sealed the club's 38th Greek championship title.

====2011–12 season====
On 19 October 2011, Holebas opened the score  with a  header against [[Borussia Dortmund]] in a 3–1 home victory on matchday 3 of the [[2011–12 UEFA Champions League group stage|Champions League group stage]]. On 3 March 2012, Holebas scored his second goal of the season in a 2–0 away league victory over [[OFI Crete F.C.|OFI Crete]], a goal that won the Superleague goal of the week award.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sport-fm.gr/videos/1024134 OΦΗ-Ολυμπιακός 0–2]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 11 March, the next week, Holebas scored Olympiacos' second goal from the penalty spot in a 3–0 league away win over [[Aris Thessaloniki F.C.|Aris]]. Olympiacos went on to retain their league title for their second season in a row,  winning their 39th Greek Championship title. On 28 April, Holebas started the [[2011–12 Greek Football Cup|Greek Cup Final]] against [[Atromitos F.C.|Atromitos]], where he missed a penalty kick in the first-half. Nonetheless, Olympiacos went on to win the Cup 2–1 after extra time, at the [[Spiros Louis Olympic Stadium|Athens Olympic Stadium]]. Holebas in the [[2011–12 Olympiacos F.C. season|2011–12 season]] scored 3 goals in 35 games in all competitions.

====2012–13 season====
On 23 September 2012, Holebas netted his first goal of the season by scoring Olympiacos' second goal in a 4–1 home league win over [[Panthrakikos F.C.|Panthrakikos]]. On 7 October, Holebas scored his second goal of the season by netting Olympiacos' first and only goal of the game in a 1–0 league home win over [[Asteras Tripoli F.C.|Asteras Tripoli]]. The next week, Holebas scored his third goal of the season by scoring the second goal in a 4–0 home league win over [[Skoda Xanthi F.C.|Skoda Xanthi]]. On 29 October, Holebas scored his fourth goal of the season by scoring Olympiacos' second goal and second equalizer in a 2–2 away league draw against Aris. Olympiacos went on to retain their league title for a third season in a row, their 40th Greek Championship title.

On 11 May 2013, Holebas started and played in the Greek Cup final, where Olympiacos went on to retain the cup for a second season in a row with a 3–1 victory after extra time over Asteras Tripoli with goals from [[David Fuster]], Rafik Djebbour and [[Djamel Abdoun]] at the Athens Olympic Stadium.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tovima.gr/sports/article/?aid=512253 Το κύπελλο στον Ολυμπιακό, οργή στον Αστέρα για τη διαιτησία]&lt;/ref&gt; Holebas the [[2012–13 Olympiacos F.C. season|2012–13 season]] scoring four goals in 40 games in all competitions, winning another league and cup double.

====2013–14 season====
In the summer of 2013, there were rumours that Holebas would join Turkish club [[Beşiktaş J.K.|Beşiktaş]], according to the Turkish media, which reported that he had agreed to sign a deal with the Black Eagles. The Turks reportedly offered the 29-year-old defender a three-year contract, with an annual salary reaching €750,000, a significant pay rise than what he was being paid by Olympiacos. The deal, however, was not completed, and Holebas decided to stay in Piraeus, subsequently signing a contract extension lasting until 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://eu.greekreporter.com/2013/08/09/holebas-from-olympiacos-to-besiktas/ | title = Holebas From Olympiacos To Besiktas?| publisher = greekreporter.com| date = 9 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 October 2013, Holebas scored his first goal of the season by netting Olympiacos's third goal with a wonderful free-kick in a 5–1 league home win over OFI Crete. On 18 January 2014, he scored his second goal of the season by netting their second goal in a 2–0 home league win over [[Levadiakos F.C.|Levadiakos]]. Olympiacos went on to retain their league title again for a fourth season in a row by winning their 41st Greek championship. He finished the [[2013–14 Olympiacos F.C. season|2013–14 campaign]] scoring two goals in 29 games in all competitions and winning another League title.

Holebas finished his very successful four-season stint with Olympiacos by netting ten toal goals in 135 games in all competitions, and also by winning the Superleague Greece four times in 2010–11, 2011–12, 2012–13 and 2013–14; the Greek Cup twice and in a row in 2011–12 and 2012–13; and participating in both the Champions League and Europa League.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.sud.worldfootball.net/spieler_profil/jose-holebas/ | title = José Holebas | publisher = worldfootball.net | accessdate = 1 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Roma===

On 30 August 2014, Holebas joined [[Serie A]] club [[A.S. Roma|Roma]] for a €1 million transfer fee from Olympiacos, plus €500,000 in bonuses. He signed a three-year contract.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.goal.com/en/news/11/transfer-zone/2014/08/31/5072331/roma-sign-jose-holebas|title =Roma sign Jose Holebas|publisher=www.goal.com|accessdate=31 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; After being presented to the media in [[Rome]] by Roma [[Chief executive officer|CEO]] [[Italo Zanzi]], Holebas stated why he joined Roma in a press conference: "I had other offers, but I decided on Roma because they are a great club at a European level. Was I expecting this move? I had discussions, it was a difficult situation because I was at the World Cup, but I am happy to be here because this is a great club. My preferred position? Certainly I will do my best. I am a left-back, playing in an attacking manner. I can also play at centre-back, but the Coach will decide."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.football-italia.net/55152/official-roma-sign-holebas|title =Official: Roma sign Holebas|publisher=football-italia.net|accessdate=6 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 September 2014, Holebas made his debut for the club, by playing the full 90 minutes in a 2–1 away league victory over [[Parma F.C.|Parma]] in their fourth match of the [[2014–15 Serie A]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = https://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/29311571|title =Parma 1-  Roma 2 |publisher=www.bbc.com|date=25 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 30 November, Holebas scored his first goal for Roma in an important 4–2 home victory over [[Inter Milan|Internazionale]] in their 13th match of Serie A to stay in touch with the top of the table. He finished his [[2014–15 A.S. Roma season|2014–15 season]] scoring one goal in 34 games in all competitions, whilst keeping veteran English international left back [[Ashley Cole]] out of the team for much of the season. For the second season in a row, Roma finished runners-up to league champions [[Juventus F.C.|Juventus]], marking for the first time since the 2009–10 season that  Holebas did not win any piece of silverware.

====Transfer speculation and controversy====
On 25 June 2015, it was reported that recently promoted [[Premier League]] club [[Watford F.C.|Watford]] were close to securing a deal for Holebas after the side confirmed interest by contacting the Italians and admiring the player's profile; they allegedly offered between €2–3 million for his services. At that point, there was a summit at Trigoria between Roma Sporting Director [[Walter Sabatini]] and the entire staff, including head coach [[Rudi Garcia]] and Simone Beccaccioli. Talks between the two clubs continued, where it was growing likely that the deal would officially be announced the following Monday. Fabio Parisi, Holebas' agent, spoke to VoceGiallorossa about the situation: "Nothing is done. There is confirmation of Watford’s interest, but there is absolutely nothing done. For now, the player's will is to have a holiday."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://romapress.us/2015/06/26/sky-italia-holebas-a-step-away-from-watford-move/|title=Sky Italia: Holebas a step away from Watford move|publisher=romapress.us|date=25 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 2 July, Watford officially announced the signing of the Greek international from Roma, which Holebas denied when he found out 24 hours later after the announcement, claiming he did not know anything about it. He later stated in an interview, "They arranged my transfer without asking me. I haven't signed anything yet, I have to see the contract first. I don't know why this has happened, I know that both Roma and Watford announced my transfer, but they'd have to talk to my representatives first. I never said I wanted to leave Roma. I'll sign after first agreeing to the terms of the contract. I can't understand why this has happened, I came back from my holiday in [[Dubai]] and everyone started telling me my transfer had been officially announced. I'm in Germany right now, how could I sign a contract?"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.standard.co.uk/sport/football/jose-holebas-denies-signing-for-watford-24-hours-after-club-announce-his-arrival-10364930.html|title=Jose Holebas denies signing for Watford, 24 hours after club announce his arrival|publisher=www.standard.co.uk|date=3 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Following that claim, and after days of confusion and wondering if Holebas was going to either continue his contact and talks with Watford and eventually sign for them, or if he was going to turn his back on Watford's offer to stay committed to the three-year deal he signed at Roma a year earlier, it was reported that on 5 July that Holebas had decided to revive his contact and discussions with Watford.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.football-italia.net/68746/holebas-revives-watford-talks|title=Holebas revives Watford talks|publisher=www.football-italia.net|date=5 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Watford===
Watford eventually officially completed the signing of Holebas for an initial fee of £1.8 million, which Roma confirmed. Roma also announced on their official website that the move could also include up to £350,000 worth of add-ons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url =http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sport/football/article-3147564/Watford-agree-signing-Roma-defender-Jose-Holebas-1-8million-deal.html|title=Watford agree signing of Roma defender Jose Holebas in £1.8million deal|publisher=www.dailymail.co.uk|date=2 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;   On 8 August 2015, he made his debut for the club, playing the full 90 minutes in a 2–2 away league draw against [[Everton F.C.|Everton]] in their opening [[2015–16 Premier League]] match and Watford's return to the top division. He picked up a yellow card in the match.

Playing just three games in all competitions in the first two-and-a-half months of the season, he  struggled to secure a first place spot in the Watford side, sitting third in the pecking order behind [[Nathan Aké]] and [[Ikechi Anya]] for the starting left-back spot. As a result, rumours circulated that he could be off-loaded already in the January transfer window.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.mirror.co.uk/sport/football/transfer-news/watford-ready-ditch-greek-international-6553963|title=Watford ready to ditch Greek international defender Jose Holebas – after just THREE GAMES|publisher=www.mirror.co.uk|date=1 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.clubcall.com/watford/holebas-heading-for-january-exit-1783511.html|title=Holebas heading for January exit|publisher=www.clubcall.com|date=29 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hornets manager [[Quique Sánchez Flores]] insisted that Holebas needed to improve to return to the team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sport/football/article-3256089/Watford-defender-Jose-Holebas-needs-improve-win-team-spot-insists-Quique-Sanchez-Flores.html|title=Watford defender Jose Holebas needs to improve to win back his first-team spot, insists Quique Sanchez Flores|publisher=www.dailymail.co.uk|date=1 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; After three months of not playing, Holebas returned to the side on 26 December to play the full 90 minutes in a  2–2 league draw away against reigning league champions [[Chelsea F.C.|Chelsea]], picking up a yellow card.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/35139930|title=BBC Sport – Chelsea 2–2 Watford|publisher=[[BBC]]|date=26 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 7 January 2016, reports surfaced that French [[Ligue 1]] giants [[Olympique de Marseille|Marseille]] were keen on signing Holebas, and that their head coach [[Míchel (footballer)|Míchel]] was seeking to rekindle the relationship that he and Holebas formed whilst working together for a season-and-a-half at Olympiacos.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.standard.co.uk/sport/football/watford-transfer-news-jose-holebas-attracting-interest-from-marseille-a3150956.html|title=Watford transfer news: Jose Holebas attracting interest from Marseille|publisher=www.standard.co.uk|date=7 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 March, Holebas complained on social media after being dropped for Aké in a game against Bournemouth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wdsport.co.uk/2016/02/jose-holebas-im-sick-of-this-s/ |title=Jose Holebas: "I’m sick of this s***" |publisher=www.wdsport.co.uk |date=1 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 March 2016, radio station ''Radyospor'' reported that Holebas had been offered to Turkish giants [[Fenerbahçe S.K. (football)|Fenerbahçe]], as a potential replacement for [[Caner Erkin]] if the latter left at the end of the season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.turkish-football.com/watford-left-back-holebas-offered-to-fenerbahce/ |title=Watford left-back offered to Fenerbahce |publisher=www.turkish-football.com |date=24 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Holebas remained at the club, and on 9 April 2016, he thought he scored his first goal  with a header just before the break in a 1–1 home draw against [[Everton F.C.|Everton]], helping the club end a poor run of four consecutive league defeats. It was later given as a Seamus Coleman own goal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.goal.com/en/match/watford-vs-everton/2043531/report |title=Watford vs Everton 1–1 |publisher=www.goal.com |date=9 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 10 September 2016, Holebas scored his first goal for the club in a 4–2 comeback away victory against [[West Ham United F.C.|West Ham United]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/sport/football/37263970|title=West Ham United 2–4 Watford |publisher=www.bbc.com|date=10 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 16 October, he scored the only goal of an away win against [[Middlesbrough F.C.|Middlesbrough]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/sport/football/37599407|title=Middlesbrough 0–1 Watford – BBC Sport|publisher=www.bbc.com|date=16 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2018, Holebas signed a new deal to keep him at Vicarage Road until the summer of 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/football/42612600 |title=Jose Holebas: Watford left-back signs new contract until 2020 |publisher=www.bbc.co.uk |date=8 January 2018 |accessdate=15 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 26 August 2018, Holebas scored with a lovely touch inside [[Andros Townsend]], looked up, and whipped in a cross that dips and swerved over [[Wayne Hennessey]] and into the top corner, giving his club a two-goal lead in a 2–1 home win game against [[Crystal Palace F.C.]] It was his first goal for the 2018–19 season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.skysports.com/football/watford-vs-c-palace/390785 |title=Watford 2–1 Crystal Palace: Roberto Pereyra, Jose Holebas seal third straight win |publisher=www.skysports.com |date=26 August 2018 |accessdate=26 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 2 September 2018, Holebas helped his club to maintain their perfect start to the Premier League season, continued to display excellent understanding down the left flank by giving two brilliant assists to [[Troy Deeney]] and [[Craig Cathcart]] in a 2–1 home win game against [[Tottenham Hotspur F.C.|Tottenham]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/football/live/2018/sep/02/watford-v-tottenham-hotspur-premier-league-live |title=Watford 2–1 Tottenham |publisher=www.theguardian.com |date=2 September 2018 |accessdate=2 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 10 November 2018, he scored his second goal in the [[2018–19 Premier League|2018–19 season]] in a 1–1 away draw against [[Southampton F.C.]] rescued a point for Watford.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.goal.com/en/news/8/main/2018/11/10/49257692/southampton-1-watford-1-holebas-cranks-up-pressure-on-hugbes |title=Southampton 1 Watford 1: Holebas cranks up pressure on Hugbes |publisher=www.goal.com |date=10 November 2018 |accessdate=10 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 December 2018, he curled in a beautiful left-footed strike from the edge of the box, giving a two-goal lead in a 3–2 home win game against [[Cardiff City F.C.|Cardiff]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.watfordfc.com/matches/match-review/match-review-watford-3-2-cardiff-city |title=Watford vs Cardiff 3-2|publisher=www.watfordfc.com |date=15 December 2018 |accessdate=15 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==International career==
[[File:20130814 AT-GR Nationalteam Griechenland 2414.JPG|thumb|300px|Holebas (second from bottom left) lining up for Greece against [[Austria national football team|Austria]] in August 2013]]

Holebas being born in [[West Germany]] was eligible to represent [[Germany national football team|Germany]] and through his [[Greeks|Greek]]-[[Uruguayans|Uruguayan]] heritage was also eligible to represent [[Greece national football team|Greece]] or [[Uruguay national football team|Uruguay]] in international football. He never appeared for any of the countries at youth level. In an interview about his International ambitions with a Greek reporter, he stated, "My dream growing up was to play for Germany, but my father is Greek so I would be happy to play for Greece." In November 2011, he received Greek citizenship as "Iosif Cholevas," &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sport24.gr/football/omades/Olympiakos/o_holebas_egine_xolevas.1428931.html|publisher=sport24.gr|title=Ο Holebas έγινε Χολέβας!|date=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and on the 11th of the same month, he officially made his debut for Greece in a friendly match against [[Russia national football team|Russia]], which ended in a 1–1 draw at the [[Georgios Karaiskakis Stadium]] in [[Piraeus]].

[[File:20130814 AT-GR Jose Holebas 2825.jpg|thumb|left|150 px|Holebas playing for Greece against Austria in 2013]]

In 2012, Holebas was part of Greece's 23-man squad for the [[UEFA Euro 2012]] finals held in [[Poland]] and [[Ukraine]]. He started the first two group games against [[Poland national football team|Poland]] in a 1–1 draw and against [[Czech Republic national football team|Czech Republic]] in a 2–1 loss and was dropped for the third match due to heavy criticism that his attacking tendency was becoming hazardous to the usually-solid defensive tactics of Greece. Nonetheless, he did come on for the final 30 minutes of the match, playing admirably and assisting Greece in holding on to the 1–0 win against Russia, which took them to the quarter-finals. Here, however, Greece fell to Germany by a score of 4–2, a defeat in which Holebas picked up a suspension for receiving another yellow card after his previous booking in the game against Russia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.theguardian.com/football/blog/2014/jun/01/world-cup-2014-greece-jose-holebas | title = World Cup 2014: Greece profile&amp;nbsp;– José Holebas| publisher = theguardian.com| date = 20 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Holebas scored his first international goal for Greece in a 1–0 victory against the [[Republic of Ireland national football team|Republic of Ireland]] in November 2012, a friendly match played at the [[Aviva Stadium]] in [[Dublin]].

Holebas' impressive 2013–14 season with Olympiacos prompted his nomination from Greek manager [[Fernando Santos (Portuguese footballer)|Fernando Santos]] as a part of the final 23-man squad for the [[2014 FIFA World Cup]] in [[Brazil]]. He played in all of Greece's matches, which included a 3–0 loss to [[Colombia national football team|Colombia]], a 0–0 draw with [[Japan national football team|Japan]], a 2–1 victory over [[Ivory Coast national football team|Ivory Coast]] in the Group Stages, and the 1–1 (5–3 penalty shoot-out) defeat to [[Costa Rica national football team|Costa Rica]] in the last 16, during which he converted his penalty kick.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/football/teams/greece/10810255/Greece-World-Cup-2014-squad.html|publisher=telegraph.co.uk|title=Greece World Cup 2014 squad|date=19 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 March 2015, two days before the crucial [[UEFA Euro 2016 qualification|Euro 2016 qualifier]] for Greece against [[Hungary national football team|Hungary]], media reports claimed that Holebas had trained normally with his Roma squad after departing from Austria on Tuesday. "On Monday José underwent a radiographic examination of which it was diagnosed that he was suffering from a left rib case injury. The player trained in [[Austria]] under an individual program but was not fit to be available to play against Hungary," the [[Hellenic Football Federation]] (HFF) said in an announcement. The HFF added that reports out of Italy cited by the Greek media "lead to completely erroneous conclusions in regards to the willingness of the player to contribute to his commitments with the national team any further."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://zeenews.india.com/sports/football/greek-football-federation-backs-injured-jose-holebas_1568865.html|publisher=zeenews.india.com|title=Greek football federation backs injured Jose Holebas|date=27 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was probably the cause for the non-call-up of the player for the national team, creating tension with new Greek manager and former national team teammate [[Georgios Karagounis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.contra.gr/Soccer/Hellas/National-Greece/holebas-ethniki-greece-hellas-karagounis-roma.3515713.html|publisher=www.contra.gr|title=Χολέμπας στο Contra.gr: "Γελοία αντίδραση το κόψιμό μου"|date=8 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 September 2015, Holebas returned to the national side after being picked by caretaker coach [[Kostas Tsanas]], where he appeared for Greece for the first time in 12 months in Greece's 0–1 home defeat against [[Finland national football team|Finland]] in a Euro 2016 qualifier in Piraeus. The defeat officially ended Greece's hopes of qualification to the [[UEFA Euro 2016|final tournament]] in [[France]] in a poor overall qualifying campaign for Greece.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uefa.com/uefaeuro/qualifiers/season=2016/matches/round=2000446/match=2013983/index.html|title=Greece 0–1 Finland|publisher=www.uefa.com|date=4 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[2018 FIFA World Cup qualification]], Holebas played his 38th and last ever cap for Greece when he came on as a second-half substitute in the Greek 2–0 home win over [[Cyprus national football team|Cyprus]] on 7 October 2016 in Piraeus. Then on 10 October 2016, after a 2–0 away win against [[Estonia national football team|Estonia]], Holebas officially announced his decision to retire from International football because he feels that it is time for the younger footballers of Greece to step up and become Greek international regulars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.naftemporiki.gr/story/1158132/apoxorei-apo-tin-ethniki-o-xolempas |title=Αποχωρεί από την Εθνική ο Χολέμπας! |publisher=www.naftemporiki.gr |date=11 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; However on 1 September 2017, Holebas admitted he had left the Greek national team due to his dislike of national team coach [[Michael Skibbe]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.contra.gr/Soccer/Hellas/National-Greece/o-xolempas-adeiase-skimpe-gia-tis-epiloges-paiktwn-sthn-ethnikh.4747512.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career statistics==
===Club===
{{updated|match played 3 March 2019}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Jose Holebas|url=http://www.soccerbase.com/players/player.sd?player_id=62066|website=Soccerbase|accessdate=19 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=J. HOLEBAS|url=https://int.soccerway.com/players/jose-holebas/16897/|website=Soccerway|accessdate=10 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Holebas, José|url=http://www.national-football-teams.com/player/45605/Jose_Holebas.html|website=National-Football-Teams|accessdate=10 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class="wikitable" style="text-align: center;"
|-
!rowspan=2|Club
!rowspan=2|Season
!colspan=3|League!!colspan=2|Cup!!colspan=2|League Cup!!colspan=2|Other!!colspan=2|Total
|-
!Division!!Apps!!Goals!!Apps!!Goals!!Apps!!Goals!!Apps!!Goals!!Apps!!Goals
|-
|rowspan=3|[[TSV 1860 Munich|1860 Munich II]]||[[2006–07 Regionalliga|2006–07]]||[[Regionalliga Süd (1994–2012)|Regionalliga Süd]]||32||12||0||0||0||0||0||0||32||12
|-
|[[2007–08 Regionalliga|2007–08]]||Regionalliga Süd||11||0||0||0||0||0||0||0||11||0
|-
!colspan=2|Total!!43!!12!!0!!0!!0!!0!!0!!0!!43!!12
|-
|rowspan=4|[[TSV 1860 Munich|1860 Munich]]||[[2007–08 2. Bundesliga|2007–08]]||[[2. Bundesliga]]||19||2||0||0||0||0||0||0||19||2
|-
|[[2008–09 2. Bundesliga|2008–09]]||2. Bundesliga||24||1||0||0||0||0||0||0||24||1
|-
|[[2009–10 2. Bundesliga|2009–10]]||2. Bundesliga||31||4||3||0||0||0||0||0||34||4
|-
!colspan=2|Total!!74!!7!!3!!0!!0!!0!!0!!0!!77!!7
|-
|rowspan=5|[[Olympiacos F.C.|Olympiacos]]||[[2010–11 Superleague Greece|2010–11]]||[[Superleague Greece]]||24||1||3||0||0||0||4||0||31||1
|-
|[[2011–12 Superleague Greece|2011–12]]||Superleague Greece||23||2||3||0||0||0||9||1||35||3
|-
|[[2012–13 Superleague Greece|2012–13]]||Superleague Greece||28||4||5||0||0||0||7||0||40||4
|-
|[[2013–14 Superleague Greece|2013–14]]||Superleague Greece||19||2||3||0||0||0||7||0||29||2
|-
!colspan=2|Total!!94!!9!!14!!0!!0!!0!!27!!1!!135!!10
|-
|[[A.S. Roma|Roma]]||[[2014–15 Serie A|2014–15]]||[[Serie A]]||24||1||1||0||0||0||9||0||34||1
|-
|rowspan=5|[[Watford F.C.|Watford]]||[[2015–16 Watford F.C. season|2015–16]]||[[Premier League]]||11||0||2||0||0||0||0||0||13||0
|-
|[[2016–17 Watford F.C. season|2016–17]]||Premier League||33||2||0||0||0||0||0||0||33||2
|-
|[[2017–18 Watford F.C. season|2017–18]]||Premier League||28||0||2||0||1||0||0||0||31||0
|-
|[[2018–19 Watford F.C. season|2018–19]]&lt;ref name=sb1819&gt;{{Soccerbase season|53961|2018|accessdate=26 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Premier League
|24||3||1||0||0||0||colspan=2|—||25||3
|-
!colspan=2|Total!!96!!6!!5!!0!!1!!0!!0!!0!!101!!6
|-
!colspan=3|Career total!!331!!35!!23!!0!!1!!0!!36!!1!!391!!36
|}

===International goals===
{| class="wikitable"
! # !! Date !! Venue !! Opponent !! Score !! Result !! Competition
|-
| 1. || 14 November 2012 || [[Dublin]], Republic of Ireland || {{fb|Republic of Ireland}} || 0–1 || Win || [[Exhibition game|Friendly]]
|}

==Honours==
'''Olympiacos'''
*[[Superleague Greece]]: [[2010–11 Superleague Greece|2010–11]], [[2011–12 Superleague Greece|2011–12]], [[2012–13 Superleague Greece|2012–13]], [[2013–14 Superleague Greece|2013–14]]
*[[Greek Football Cup|Greek Cup]]: [[2011–12 Greek Football Cup|2011–12]], [[2012–13 Greek Football Cup|2012–13]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{Fussballdaten|holebasjose|José Holebas}}
*{{Soccerbase}}

{{Navboxes
| title = Greece squads
| bg = #0000cd
| fg = #FFFFFF
| bordercolor = silver
| list1 = 
{{Greece squad UEFA Euro 2012}}
{{Greece squad 2014 FIFA World Cup}}
}}
{{Watford F.C. squad}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Holebas, Jose}}
[[Category:1984 births]]
[[Category:2. Bundesliga players]]
[[Category:2014 FIFA World Cup players]]
[[Category:A.S. Roma players]]
[[Category:Expatriate footballers in England]]
[[Category:Expatriate footballers in Greece]]
[[Category:Expatriate footballers in Italy]]
[[Category:German people of Greek descent]]
[[Category:German people of Uruguayan descent]]
[[Category:German expatriates in England]]
[[Category:Greek expatriate sportspeople in England]]
[[Category:Greece international footballers]]
[[Category:Greek expatriate footballers]]
[[Category:German footballers]]
[[Category:Greek footballers]]
[[Category:Uruguayan footballers]]
[[Category:Greek people of Uruguayan descent]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Naturalized citizens of Greece]]
[[Category:Olympiacos F.C. players]]
[[Category:People from Aschaffenburg]]
[[Category:Premier League players]]
[[Category:Serie A players]]
[[Category:Superleague Greece players]]
[[Category:TSV 1860 Munich players]]
[[Category:TSV 1860 Munich II players]]
[[Category:UEFA Euro 2012 players]]
[[Category:Watford F.C. players]]
[[Category:Association football fullbacks]]
[[Category:Association football midfielders]]
[[Category:Footballers from Bavaria]]</text>
      <sha1>0vbp1e4c1i81d2ek5yc9i8v4abuk2u6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
